<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [

]>

<section id="sn-configuring-usb-device-access">
  <title>Configuring USB device access (Linux only)</title>
  <para>
    Linux is by default a multi-user system, so it has to have a policy to
    determine who can access various devices. This includes those that can
    be plugged into to a USB port.
  </para>

  <para>
    For devices known to the operating system (which these days includes
    most digital cameras, scanners, MIDI interfaces etc.), a logged-in user
    will be granted access automatically. However, for devices that the OS
    doesn't recognize (even if there is software on it that can use it),
    this is not the case. It is possible to configure Linux to reverse this
    policy and grant all users access to all devices, but this is not
    recommended for security reasons.
  </para>

  <section id="usb-access-tranzport">
    <title>Configuring Access to a Frontier Design Tranzport</title>
    <para>
      Using the Tranzport on Linux requires a couple of extra steps to
      enable non-administrative users to access the device.
    </para>

    <para>
      First, you need to login as the administrative user ("root"). Then put
      the following into a new file called
      <filename>/etc/hotplug/usb/tranzport</filename>
    </para>
<screen>
#!/bin/sh

if [ $ACTION = "add" ] &amp;&amp; [ -f $DEVICE ] ; then
    chmod 0666 $DEVICE
fi
exit 0
</screen>
    <para>
      Then make sure that the file is executable by running
    </para>
<screen>
chmod +x /etc/hotplug/usb/tranzport
</screen>
    <para>
      Second, edit the file <filename>/etc/hotplug/usb.usermap</filename> by
      adding the following 2 lines to the end of it (make sure that the 2nd
      line is not split across multiple lines, even though it is very long):
    </para>
<screen>
# Frontier Design Tranzport
tranzport            0x0000      0x165b   0x8101    0x0000       0x0000      0x00         0x00            0x00            0x00          0x00               0x00               0x00000000
</screen>
    <para>
      After doing these steps, the next time you plugin your Tranzport it
      will be accessible to you as a regular user.
    </para>
  </section>
<!--
	<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
		href="Some_Subsection.xml" />
	-->
</section>
