<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [

]>

<section id="editor-window-timeline">
  <title>Timeline</title>
  <para>
    At the top of the track display area is the timeline display. This
    consists of a number of rulers, a meter track, a tempo track and the
    marker display.
  </para>

  <para>
    The available rulers include:
  </para>

  <table id="tbl-rulers">
    <title>Ruler Types</title>
    <tgroup cols = "2">
      <colspec colnum="1" colname="Ruler Type" colwidth="1"/>
      <colspec colnum="2" colname="Description" colwidth= "2"/>
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>
            Ruler Type
          </entry>

          <entry>
            Description
          </entry>
        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>
            Frames
          </entry>

          <entry>
            this ruler measures audio frames. The number of audio frames per
            second depends on the sample rate in use.
          </entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>
            SMPTE
          </entry>

          <entry>
            this ruler displays SMPTE timecode. The SMPTE format (25fps,
            30fps, drop frame etc) is selected in the Options Editor
            option_editor.
          </entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>
            Min:Sec
          </entry>

          <entry>
            this ruler displays time in minutes+seconds, measured since the
            start of the session.
          </entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>
            BBT
          </entry>

          <entry>
            <para>
              (Bars,Beats,Ticks) this ruler displays positions based on the
              tempo map.
            </para>
          </entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>

  <para>
    To show or hide one or more of the rulers, click on the area to the left
    of their names. A menu will popup that has a check item for each
    available ruler. Click on the name of the ruler to toggle its
    visibility.
  </para>

  <para>
    The tempo and meter tracks display the tempo map for the session. The
    tempo track contains 1 or more tempo change points, with a default tempo
    of 120 beats per minute. The meter track contains 1 or more meter change
    points, with an initial default meter of 4/4.
  </para>

  <para>
    on a tempo/meter change point to edit it. Click in the tempo/meter track
    to add a new change point. Click and drag on a change point to move it.
    on a tempo/meter change point to remove it.
  </para>

  <para>
    There is more information on using the timeline in editing_basics.
  </para>
<!--
								<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
									href="Some_Subsection.xml" />
								-->
</section>
