<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [

]>

<section id="editor-window-region-list">
  <title>Region List</title>
  <para>
    To the right of the track display is the region list, which uses a tree
    display to show all regions in the session. There are sections in the
    region list, &#8220;Captured&#8221; and &#8220;External&#8221;.
    &#8220;Captured&#8221; contains all regions that were either recorded by
    Ardour or imported as native audio files. &#8220;External&#8221;contains
    regions created using audio files external to Ardour (from a sample
    library, for example).
  </para>

  <section id="region-list-organization">
    <title>Organization of the region list</title>
    <para>
      In both sections of the region list, any regions containing multiple
      channels will have its name followed by &#8220;[N]&#8221; where N is a
      number indicating the number of channels. Any region that ends in
      &#8220;-N&#8221;, where N is a number, is a region that describes an
      entire audio file. Any region that ends in &#8220;.N&#8221; is a
      region that describes part of an audio file. Any subtree within the
      region list can be hidden or displayed by clicking on the box left of
      its name.
    </para>

    <para>
      Within the Captured part of the tree, each track is represented by its
      own subtree (strictly speaking, its not each track but each playlist
      that is represented). Within that subtree is an entry for each take
      recorded for that track. Remember that each take is stored as one and
      audio files (strictly, one per channel). Within the take tree is an
      entry for each region created from that take.
    </para>

    <para>
      Within the External part of the tree, there is a subtree for each
      audio file embedded into the session. Within that subtree are entries
      for each region created from that audio file.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="region-list-operations">
    <title>Region list operations</title>
    <para>
      Click on the box to the left of the name of part of the tree to
      hide/show that part of the subtree.
    </para>

    <para>
      Click the name of a region and then drag it to the track display area
      to insert a region into a track.
    </para>

    <para>
      Click on the title bar of the region list to display a menu allowing
      you to
    </para>

    <table id="tbl-region-list-operations-menu">
      <title>Region List Context Menu</title>
      <tgroup cols = "2">
        <colspec colnum="1" colname="Snap Option" colwidth="1"/>
        <colspec colnum="2" colname="Action" colwidth= "2"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Menu Item
            </entry>

            <entry>
              Description
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Find
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              Show/Hide All
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>
                fully expand or collapse the region list
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              Sort
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              Display Automatic Regions normally,
            </entry>

            <entry>
              Ardour does not display regions created as a result of a side
              effect of user actions. If this option is selected, all
              regions will be included in the region list.
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              Import audio files
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>
                copy (and if necessary convert) audio files into the
                session. See Importing for more details.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              Embed audio file
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>
                embed external audio files into the session. No new files
                are created, and no format conversion is done. See
                [[editing:Embedding]] for more details.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>
<!--
							<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
								href="Some_Subsection.xml" />
							-->
</section>
