<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [

]>

<section id="sn-editor-window">
  <title>The Editor</title>
  <para>
    Ardour provides two ways of viewing a session: the Editor and the Mixer.
    The Editor shows the session by representing tracks as horizontal
    timeline displays, with material within the tracks (audio, MIDI, video,
    automation data, etc.) arranged along the horizontal (time) axis. The
    Mixer shows the session by representing tracks as mixer strips, with
    controls for gain, record enable, soloing and so forth. More abstractly,
    the Editor represents the time based aspects of a session, whereas the
    Mixer represents the signal flow.
  </para>

  <para>
    However, it is quite possible to control the signal flow aspects from
    within the Editor as well, without the comprehensive overview that the
    Mixer provides. For some sessions, especially during the early stages of
    a session, the Editor may be the only window you need to use.
  </para>

  <section id="editor-window-layout">
    <title>Editor Window Layout</title>
    <para>
      Lets survey the basic layout of the editor window:
    </para>

    <para>
      The transport controls are in a tearoff window at the top of the
      editor, and are described in transport_window.
    </para>
  </section>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
		href="editor_window_controls.xml" />
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
		href="editor_window_track_list.xml" />
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
		href="editor_window_group_list.xml" />
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
		href="editor_window_region_list.xml" />
  <section id="editor-window-chunk-list">
    <title>Chunk List</title>
    <para>
      Below the region list is the Chunk List, which provides a visual list
      of all "chunks". Chunks are collections (possibly discontiguous) of
      sections.
    </para>
  </section>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
	  	href="track_display.xml" />
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
		href="editor_window_timeline.xml" />
  <section id="editor-window-track-controls">
    <title>Track Controls</title>
    <para>
      Each track has a set of controls on its left side. Which controls are
      present varies depending on the type of track (audio, bus, automation,
      MIDI, etc.). Every track type has a "hide" button marked with a cross.
      Click on this to hide the track.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="editor-window-track-views">
    <title>Track Views</title>
    <para>
      This is where all editing takes place. The track views contain region
      objects, curve control points, lines and other items that can be
      added, removed, copied, cut and pasted. See editing_basics for more
      information on editing.
    </para>
  </section>
<!--
	<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
		href="Some_Subsection.xml" />
	-->
</section>
