<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [

]>

<section id="sn-exporting-to-cd">
  <sectioninfo>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <personname>
          <firstname>Nick</firstname>
          <surname>Mainsbridge</surname>
        </personname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
  </sectioninfo>
  <title>Exporting to CD</title>
  <section id="table-of-contents">
    <title>Table of Contents </title>
    <para>
      A Table of Contents is a description of the data stored on a medium.
      In the case of audio Cds, the TOC comes in the form of PQ data which
      is intermingled with the audio data whaen the CD is burnt. Because PQ
      data isn't part of 'normal' audio file formats such as wav or aiff,
      this information must be stored in a separate file on your computer (a
      CUE or TOC file) ready for use by your CD burning software which will
      combine the two.
    </para>

    <para>
      At the moment, Ardour can export TOC and CUE files containing the
      red-book related fields Track, Index, ISRC, SCMS and Preemphasis. The
      CD-TEXT fields TITLE, COMPOSER, PERFORMER and disc title are also
      supported.
    </para>

    <para>
      Range markers in Ardour can be 'promoted' to become CD tracks in the
      locations window. Marks (point markers) can be promoted to be CD
      Indexes in the same window. All TOC/CUE export operations hinge on
      this.
    </para>

    <para>
      Assuming you have several songs on your timeline laid out so that
      their spacing and level is 'correct' as you hear it, you should then
      set ranges that represent the start and end points of each track,
      These will become the start and end points on your CD. The start times
      are all rounded down to the previous CD frame (Of which there are
      75/second) on export, so if you want to hear the exact point that your
      CD player will start from, select 'CD frames' as your snap setting
      while you do this. If you want track indexes (nobody does, but they're
      there), set a location marker for each desired index.
    </para>

    <para>
      The locations dialog is useful here, as you can just 'go' to a point
      to audition the exact position of a marker/range.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="pregap">
    <title> Pregap </title>
    <para>
      A word about pregap:
    </para>

    <para>
      A 'normal' redbook CD should have a blank (digital black) space of 2
      seconds before the first modulation called the pregap. Ideally, your
      first song will have been placed at 2 seconds when you began, but you
      can always drag the whole collection of songs to the right position
      fairly easily at this point.
    </para>

    <para>
      Also, note that this 2 second rule can be fun to break. You can make
      the pregap as long as you like.. even hide whole songs in there. The
      player will still play track one when the disc is inserted. Only those
      listeners with the urge to rewind beyond the beginning will find your
      hidden song/dog bark. Also keep in mind that there is a pregap for
      each song. It starts where the previous song ends. In other words, if
      you leave a gap in the ranges between songs 2 &amp; 3, that gap will
      only play for those listening through the entire CD. Anyone skipping
      directly to 3 will miss your secret 'long' intro.
    </para>

    <para>
      After setting a non-overlapping range for each track (overlapping CD
      tracks are removed on export, from left to right, as are indexes that
      aren't inside a track), open the locations window and make your ranges
      into track markers by clicking the CD button. Fill in whatever
      information you feel is necessary in the boxes below. Unused fields
      will be ignored as far as the exported TOC/CUE file is concerned.
    </para>

    <para>
      CD-TEXT track titles are taken from the range's name. The CD-TEXT
      title of the CD is taken from the session name (i should have told you
      that first, right?).
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
        Pre-emphasis is there for those strange types that use it (they also
        use track indexes). You almost certainly don't want pre-emphasis. A
        valid ISRC is all capitals, 12 characters.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section id="cue-files">
    <title> Cue Files </title>
    <para>
      Cue files have no notion of 'the end'. Its a drag. They think the end
      of the file is the end of the last track. If you want to use CUE
      files, you have to make sure that the session end marker is snapped to
      CD frames (before you export, of course), or else use the -pad option
      when you burn.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="export-the-session">
    <title> Export The Session </title>
    <para>
      Now export the session to a file (16bit 44.1kHz for CD), selecting
      your preferred cuefile type (TOC or CUE). The TOC/CUE file is written
      to the same directory as your audio file, and has the same name, only
      with '.toc' or '.cue' appended. Usually you will only be selecting the
      two master outputs to export, with output 1 always being 'left'. The
      export is post fader and panner. Don't assume that the sound will be
      identical after you have truncated/dithered to 16 bits. It can be
      worthwhile to experiment with different dither settings when making
      your export.
    </para>

    <para>
      To check out the details without burning
    </para>
<screen>
cdrdao show-toc blah.wav.toc
</screen>
    <para>
      to correct a problem, make your changes, then use the 'export toc file
      only' option. If you have to change the session end marker, you'll
      have to re-export your audio file.
    </para>

    <para>
      To burn
    </para>
<screen>
cdrdao write /home/britney/globalsmash.wav.toc
</screen>
    <para>
      One last thing:
    </para>

    <para>
      If you don't make any CD Track ranges and export a TOC/CUE file, the
      entire session is treated as one track with no pregap. Indexes, if
      present, will be honoured.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="ddp-support">
    <title>FAQ </title>
    <para>
      Why no DDP? ( http://www.dcainc.com/products/ddp/ )
    </para>

    <para>
      A: DCA have been kind enough to get in touch. Hopefully they will
      allow a GPL implementaton soon.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="catalog-numbers">
    <title>What about catalog numbers for the CD?</title>
    <para>
      A: coming eventually.. we need a tab for session-wide variables like
      these. where to put it? in the export dialog or the options menu?
    </para>
  </section>
<!--
	<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
		href="Some_Subsection.xml" />
	-->
</section>
