<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [

]>

<section id="sn-formatting-conventions">
  <title>Formatting Conventions</title>
  <section id="typography">
    <title>Typography</title>
    <para>
      This manual uses a few conventions to indicate key commands, menu
      choices and other user interactions:
    </para>

    <para>
      Key commands such as <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>a</keycap>
      </keycombo> mean "Hold down the Ctrl key and press the 'a' key".
    </para>

    <para>
      The names of on-screen buttons are shown like this
      <guibutton>Button</guibutton>
    </para>

    <para>
      The name of a menu item is shown like <guimenuitem>This</guimenuitem>,
      and nested menu items will appear as <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Menu</guimenu> <guisubmenu>Sub Menu</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="admonitions">
    <title>Admonitions</title>
    <para>
      Admonitions are set apart from the main text and are meant to draw
      your attention to pieces of information. In the order of how critical
      the information is to you, these items are marked as follows:
    </para>

    <note>
      <title>Note</title>
      <para>
        A note is typically information that you need to understand the
        behavior of Ardour.
      </para>
    </note>
    <tip><title>Tip</title>
      <para>
        A tip is typically an alternative way of performing a task.
      </para>
    </tip>
    <important>
      <title>Important</title>
      <para>
        The important admonition is used to draw attention to parts of the
        interface that may be overlooked or certain settings that are vital
        in determining the behaviour of ardour.
      </para>
    </important>

    <warning>
      <title>Warning</title>
      <para>
        The warning admonition is used where an action may result in
        consequences that are unintended or permanent such as changes to the
        session that can not be undone or the removal of files.
      </para>
    </warning>
  </section>

  <section id="mouse-buttons">
    <title>Mouse Buttons</title>
    <para>
      You might be used to terms like "right mouse button", "left mouse
      button" etc. These are widely used, but they can be very confusing for
      left-handed people, or people using mice with many buttons arranged in
      an unconventional way. Ardour is typically used with mice equipped
      with at least 3 buttons that can be remapped for left- and
      right-handed users, making it hard to unambiguously define "left" and
      "right" in a useful way.
    </para>

    <para>
      If you are right-handed and use a conventional mouse, then
      <mousebutton>Button1</mousebutton> corresponds to "left mouse button",
      <mousebutton>Button2</mousebutton> to "middle mouse button" and
      <mousebutton>Button3</mousebutton> to "right mouse button". Otherwise,
      the numbered button nomenclature refers to the same button numbers as
      defined by your X Window configuration.
    </para>

    <para>
      If you see instructions to use <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <mousebutton>Button1</mousebutton> </keycombo> , it means "Hold down
      the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key and click
      <mousebutton>Button1</mousebutton> ".
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="select-choose">
    <title>Select/Choose</title>
    <para>
      In conventional English, "select" and "choose" are often used as
      synonyms. In this manual, we use them to mean quite different things:
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <title></title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Select</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When you select something, it will stay selected. Putting a
            check-mark in a box, for example, would be referred to as
            "selecting" that box. This is also true for menu items that
            enable or disable options ("select Big Clock from the Windows
            menu", for example) and various editing functions.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Choose</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            "Choosing" involves clicking or using the keyboard to accomplish
            a one-time action. A command to save the current session might
            be described as, "Choose Save from the Session menu.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
<!--
	<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
		href="Some_Subsection.xml" />
	-->
</section>
