<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [

]>

<chapter id="sn-problems-bugs-known-issues">
  <title>Problems, Bugs and Known Issues</title>
  <section id="known-issues">
    <title> Known Issues </title>
    <para>
      This section documents known issues with the all versions of Ardour up
      to and including 1.0. It is not a replacement for our
      <ulink url="http://tracker.ardour.org/">bug tracking system</ulink>,
      but instead summarizes some known issues that are likely to be
      encountered by users and are not in the process of being fixed.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          creating 3rd level feedback loops (e.g. bus 1 feeds bus 2 feeds
          bus 3; bus 3 feeds bus 1) may prevent a session from loading
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          ardour's interpretation of "beats per minute" is different from
          most other programs and from convention. 1 "beat" is whatever the
          meter in effect defines. Thus, 120 bpm in a 4/4 meter is 120
          quarter notes per minute; 120 bpm in a 3/8 meter is 120 eighth
          notes per minute.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          copying or cut-n-pasting two (or more) regions that have a
          crossfade between them to a new location or a new track does not
          copy the crossfade. Until a future version of Ardour changes this,
          you are advised to do region editing first, and create crossfades
          second.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          it is not possible to create pan automation control points using
          the mouse for stereo (or higher channel count) tracks and busses.
          you can create automation for these configurations by recording
          panning motion, and you can edit the data using the mouse.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          when importing an audio file directly into a track, there are no
          choices for the quality level of any necessary sample rate
          conversion. On any system that Ardour is running on, there is
          almost certainly a utility called
          <command>sndfile-resample</command> which uses the same sample
          rate conversion library as Ardour. This utility offers a great
          deal of control over the sample rate conversion process, including
          quality levels. Ardour uses the "best" quality internally. If you
          want a different quality, you can use this tool to produce a
          rate-converted file at the correct speed, and then import that
          into Ardour.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          when timestretch is used to alter the length of a region, any
          region-specific gain envelope is lost. The new region has the
          default unity gain throughout its duration.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          if you overdub on a playlist in an area containing cross-fades,
          the cross-fades will still be audible in spite of the newly
          overdubbed material being "on top" of them. Workaround is to mute
          or remove the crossfades before overdubbing. As a corollary to
          this, creating crossfades that span other crossfades will not work
          correctly in this version of Ardour.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
<!--
	<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
		href="Some_Subsection.xml" />
	-->
</chapter>
