<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [

]>

<section id="sn-main-windows">
  <title>Windows</title>
  <para>
    When Ardour starts without a session, there is just a single window
    visible which we call the editor. However, the program has many more
    windows that can be displayed for various purposes:
  </para>

  <note>
    <para>
      All Ardour windows have their WMCLASS property set to 'ardour', so
      that you can configure your window manager to handle them in a certain
      way if you wish to.
    </para>
  </note>

  <section id="editor-window-summary">
    <title>Editor Window</title>
    <para>
      This is the primary Ardour window. It contains the main menubar, plus
      several tear-off windows, and the editor itself.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="transport-bar-summary">
    <title>Transport Bar Window</title>
    <para>
      This window provides complete control over all of Ardour's transport
      functionality. it is initially attached to the editor window, but can
      be torn off and kept as an independent window if you prefer.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="mixer-window-summary">
    <title>Mixer Window</title>
    <para>
      This window will be displayed automatically whenever a Session is
      loaded, and provides a representation of the Session that is modelled
      on a mixing console. Each track and bus has its own Mixer Strip, and
      there are also various lists for things like Mix Groups.
    </para>

    <para>
      A more precise way to think about the difference between the editor
      and the mixer is that the editor is primarily for controlling the time
      flow of the Session, whereas the mixer is primarily for controlling
      the signal flow.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="location-and-marker-display-window-summary">
    <title>Location and Marker Display Window</title>
    <para>
      This window is used to display, edit and set various Locations and
      markers within a Session.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="options-editor-window-summary">
    <title>Options Editor Window</title>
    <para>
      This window is used to set the many global and per-session options for
      Ardour.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="track-bus-inspector-window-summary">
    <title>Track/Bus Inspector Window</title>
    <para>
      This optional window provides a single point of control for
      configuring all I/O and processing for every track and bus. It doesn't
      provide anything not offered by other windows, but it does group
      several things together in one place. You may prefer to use or not use
      this window.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="big-clock-window-summary">
    <title>Big Clock Window</title>
    <para>
      This optional window provides a display of the playhead position in a
      large font, readable from some distance. it can be useful when using
      Ardour to record yourself and you need or want to keep track of time.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
