<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [

]>

<section id="sn-mixer-window">
	<title>The Mixer</title>
	<para>
		The mixer window provides a view of the session that mimics a traditional
		hardware mixing console. Rather than focusing on the arranging of regions
		along a timeline, the mixer is designed to allow you to manipulate the
		signal flow elements of a session - gain control, plugins, bussing and so
		forth.
	</para>

	<para>
		The left area of the mixer contains three small vertical panes which allow
		various operations to be made on the larger area, which of course represents
		a mixing console.
	</para>

	<para>
		The lines that outline the three smaller panes all have a small square near
		their vertices. This square can be used to resize the four panes that form
		the mixer window. Dragging each of these squares with the left mouse button
		will move the border.
	</para>

	<section id="mixer-window-layout">
		<title>Mixer Window Layout</title>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/mixer.png"/>
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
			href="mixer_strips.xml" />
		<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
			href="mixer_strip_list.xml" />
		<section id="mixer-window-group-list">
			<title> Group List </title>
			<para>
				The group list pane provides an interface to create and control the state
				of the mix groups present on the mixer. Mix groups provide a method of
				linking faders together, so that a movement on one fader will translate to
				all the other faders in the group.
			</para>

			<para>
				A new session will contail one group, called all. This preset group refers
				to all mixer strips?? <emphasis>what is 'all' doing here?</emphasis> Any
				new groups you create will be listed in this pane. Left clicking the
				<guibutton>Mix Groups</guibutton> button will open a window titled
				<literal>Name for a new mix group</literal>, which contains a dark text area.
				Enter a name for your new mix group in the text area. Left clicking
				<guibutton>cancel</guibutton> will close the <literal>Name for a new mix
				group</literal> window. The group list will be unaffected. Left clicking
			<guibutton>OK</guibutton> will create a new mix group. The new group will be
				listed in the group list pane with an empty box next to it's name. All
				mixer strips will now contain the name of the new group in their
				<guibutton>group</guibutton> button. Selecting the new group in a mixer
				strip will assign control of that channel's gain fader to the selected
				group, but <emphasis>only if the group is active</emphasis>. Left clicking
				the box next to the group name will activate the group.
			</para>

			<para>
				At the bottom right of the group list, a square box provides a method for
				resizing the pane. Holding down the left mouse button while dragging the
				square vertically will move the lower border of the group list.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="mixer-window-snapshot-list">
			<title> Snapshot List </title>
			<para>
				Track Name Group Button Input Selector Solo Button Mute Button Polarity
				Button Track Speed Control Record Enable Button Automation Record Button
				Automation Playback Button Pre/Post Button Gain Display Unit Selector Gain
				Level Display Peak Meter Gain Fader Meters Output Selector
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</section>
