<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [

]>

<section id="mixer-window-strip-list">
  <title> Strip List </title>
  <para>
    The Strip List provides a simple interface to the layout of the mixer
    strips on the mixer. Mixer strips on the mixer have two possible states
    - visible and hidden. Mixer strips can also be placed in any order on
    the mixer. Rearranging the order of the mixer strips has no effect on
    the signal flow of the session. The names of all tracks in your session
    are listed in their current order. Hidden mixer strips are darker in
    colour than visible ones. A single left click on a track name will
    remove the track's mixer strip from the mixer, and changing the colour
    of the item on the strip list. This action has no effect on signal flow.
    Dragging a track name vertically with the left mouse button will
    rearrange the mixer to reflect the order selected when the mouse button
    is released. Clicking the word "Strip" at the top of the strip list will
    open a drop-down list of shortcuts to actions that change the strip list
    (and consequently the state of the mixer).
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <title>Strip List Context Menu</title>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenuitem>show all</guimenuitem></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          sets all hidden mixer strips to the visible state
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenuitem>hide all</guimenuitem></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          sets all visible mixer strips to the hidden state.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenuitem>show all AudioTrack Mixer Strips</guimenuitem></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          sets all hidden mixer strips that are audio tracks to the visible
          state
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenuitem>hide all AudioTrack Mixer Strips</guimenuitem></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          sets all visible mixer strips that are audio tracks to the hidden
          state.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenuitem>show all AudioBus Mixer Strips</guimenuitem></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          sets all hidden mixer strips that are audio buses to the visible
          state
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenuitem>hide all AudioBus Mixer Strips</guimenuitem></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          sets all visible mixer strips that are audio buses to the hidden
          state.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
    At the bottom right of the strip list, a square box provides a method
    for resizing the pane. Holding down the left mouse button while dragging
    the square vertically will move the lower border of the strip list.
  </para>
<!--
	<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
		href="Some_Subsection.xml" />
	-->
</section>
