<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [

<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "./entities.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;

]>

<section id="sn-soloing-tracks">
  <title>Soloing Tracks</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Tracks</primary>
    <secondary>Soloing</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
    "Soloing" a track refers to changing some aspect of the signal flow
    through Ardour that makes it possible to listen to one (or just a few)
    tracks at a time. It is often done during mixing and mastering to help
    an audio engineer listen carefully to parts of the mix.
  </para>

  <para>
    Tracks may be soloed at any time. When one or more tracks are soloed,
    all non-soloedntracks will no longer be audible.
  </para>

  <para>
    Soloing tracks does not affect the solo status of busses, nor vice
    versa. That is, soloing a track leaves all busses audible and soloing a
    track leaves all tracks "audible". You may not actually be able to hear
    the "audible" material if it is routed through a non-soloed bus.
  </para>

  <para>
    This design is intended to allow FX busses and master outs to be useful
    even when soloing. Soloing is made significantly more complex by the
    presence of control outs (see control_outs_soloing for more details on
    soloing with control outs).
  </para>

  <section id="rude-solo-light">
    <title>Rude Solo Light</title>
    <para>
      Whenever one or more tracks are soloed, the "rude solo light" in the
      transport window will flash. You can cancel any current solos by
      clicking on the "rude solo light".
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="solo-modes">
    <title>Solo modes</title>
    <para>
      Ardour has two solo modes.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <title></title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>solo latch</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            soloing a track adds it to the set of soloed tracks, so you may
            have any number of soloed tracks.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>solo unlatch</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            soloing a track unsolos any other soloed track, so you can have
            only one soloed track at a time.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section id="changing-solo-mode">
    <title>Changing Solo Mode</title>
    <para>
      To change the solo mode, goto the Options editor (options_editor) and
      view the <guilabel>Misc</guilabel> tab.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="soloing-a-track">
    <title>Soloing a Track</title>
    <para>
      To toggle the solo state of a track, click on the solo button in
      either the mixer strip for the track or the track controls section in
      the editor.
    </para>

    <para>
      To toggle the solo state of all tracks in an edit or mix group, use
      Ctrl1 on the solo button of a track in the group. If you do this in
      the Editor, the edit group will be used; in the Mixer, the mix group
      will be used.
    </para>

    <para>
      To toggle the solo state of all tracks, use
      <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap><mousebutton>Button1</mousebutton></keycombo>
      on a track solo button.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="solo-safe">
    <title>Solo safe</title>
    <para>
      To protect a track's current solo status, use Shift1 on that track's
      solo button. The color of the button will change to a pale blue to
      indicate "solo safe" status. No changes to the solo state for that
      track are possible until "solo safe" has been unset for the track.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="momentary-solo">
    <title>Momentary solo</title>
    <para>
      Use 2 on a track's solo button to solo the track for as long as the
      mouse button is pressed.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
