<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [

]>

<section id="sn-working-with-regions">
	<title>Working with Regions</title>
	<para>
		Regions are the basic elements of editing and composing in Ardour. Each
		region represents a single, contiguous section of one or more audio files.
		Regions are defined by a fixed set of attributes:
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				the source audio file(s) they represent
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				a starting point in the audio file(s)
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				a length
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>
		When placed into a <glossterm linkend="gt-playlist">playlist</glossterm>,
		they gain additional attributes:
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				a position along the timeline
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				a layer
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>
		There are <emphasis>other attributes</emphasis> as well, but they do not
		define the region. Things you should know about regions:
	</para>

	<variablelist>
		<title></title>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Regions are Cheap</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					By themselves, regions do not consume hardly any of your computer's
					resources. Each region requires a small amount of memory, and represents
					a rather small amount of CPU work if placed into an active track. So,
					don't worry about creating regions whenever you need to.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>Regions are not audio files</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Although a region can represent an entire audio file, they are never
					equivalent to an audio file. Most regions represent just parts of an
					audio file(s) on disk, and removing a region from a track has nothing to
					do with removing the audio file(s) from the disk ((the
					<emphasis>Destroy</emphasis> operation, one of Ardour's few destructive
					operations, can affect this)). Changing the length of a region has no
					effect on the audio file(s) on disk. Splitting and copying regions does
					not alter the audio file in anyway, nor does it create new audio files
					((the <emphasis>Export</emphasis> , <emphasis>Bounce</emphasis> and
					<emphasis>Reverse</emphasis> operations do create new audio files)).
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<section id="region-naming">
		<title>Region Naming</title>
		<para>
			Regions are initially named using either:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					the name of the playlist for which they were recorded
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					the name of the embedded/imported audio file they represent
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<section id="whole-file-region-names">
			<title>Whole File Region Names</title>
			<para>
				These are not audio files, but regions that represent the full extent of
				an audio file. Every time a new recording is done, or a new file is
				embedded/imported, a new region is created that represents the entire
				audio file(s) This region will have the name of the playlist/original
				file, followed by a "-" and then a number.
			</para>

			<para>
				For recorded regions, the number will increase each time a new recording
				is made. So, for example, if there is a playlist called "Didgeridoo", the
				first recorded whole file region for that playlist will be called
				"Digderidoo-1". The next one will be "Digeridoo-2" and so on.
			</para>

			<para>
				For imported/embedded files, the region name will be based on the file
				name, but with any final suffix (e.g. ".wav" or ".aiff") removed.
			</para>

			<para>
				Normally, whole file regions are not inserted into tracks/playlists, but
				regions derived from them are. The whole-file versions live in the editor
				region list where they act as an organizing mechanism for regions that are
				derived from them.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="normal-region-names">
			<title>Normal Region Names</title>
			<para>
				When a region is inserted into a track/playlist, its initial name will end
				in a version number, such as ".1" or ".103". For a recorded region, if the
				whole file region was "Hang drum-1", then the region in the track will
				appear with the name "Hang drum-1.1". For an imported/embedded region, if
				the whole file region was "Bach:Invention3", then the region in the track
				will appear with the name "Bach:Invention3.1".
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="copied-region-names">
			<title>Copied Region Names</title>
			<para>
				If the region is a copy of another region, it will begin life with the
				same name as the original. When an operation is carried out that modifies
				one of the copies, that particular copy will be renamed by incrementing
				the version number.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="renaming-regions">
			<title>Renaming Regions</title>
			<para>
				You can rename a region at any time. Use the <emphasis>region context
				menu</emphasis> to popup the rename dialog. The new name does not need to
				have a version number in it (in fact, it probably should not). The region
				will retain its name until it is modified after being copied.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="selecting-regions">
		<title>Selecting Regions</title>
		<para>
			In general, operations on regions apply to whichever regions are currently
			<emphasis>selected</emphasis> .
		</para>

		<para>
			To select a single region, click on it using
			<mousebutton>Button1</mousebutton>.
		</para>

		<para>
			To add an unselected region to the currently selected regions, click on it
			using
			<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><mousebutton>Button1</mousebutton></keycombo>.
		</para>

		<para>
			To remove a selected region from the currently selected regions, click on
			it using
			<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><mousebutton>Button1</mousebutton></keycombo>.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="removing-regions">
		<title>Removing Regions</title>
		<para>
			Select the region(s) to be removed. Then press the "Delete" key or use the
			standard key binding for "Cut" (
			<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>X</keycap></keycombo> by default).
		</para>

		<para>
			Note that "removing" a region is a non-destructive operation. It has no
			effect on the audio file(s) stored on disk. If you really want to
			destructively remove the region, use the context menu for the region which
			has a "Destroy" item. This is not guaranteed to remove the audio file from
			your disk storage, but it generally will.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="moving-regions">
		<title>Moving Regions</title>
		<para>
			To move a region, make sure you are in <emphasis>object</emphasis> mouse
			mode. Move the mouse pointer into the waveform display part of the region,
			press <mousebutton>Button1</mousebutton> and drag. The region will follow the
			mouse pointer as you move it around. By default, the region can move freely
			along the timeline - see <xref linkend="sn-snap-settings"/> for information on how to
			force the region to align to certain kinds of points along the timeline.
		</para>

		<para>
			To move a region from one track to another, simply start a move as
			described above, but move the mouse pointer into the desired track. The
			region will follow the mouse pointer. Note that if you have other kinds of
			"tracks" visible, the region will remain where it is as the mouse pointer
			moves across them, and will then jump to the new track. This serves as a
			visual reminder that you cannot drag an audio region into an automation
			track or a bus, for example.
		</para>

		<section id="moving-more-than-one-region">
			<title>Moving more than one region</title>
			<para>
				To move multiple regions, select them before moving. Then click+drag on
				one of the selected regions. All the regions will move, keeping their
				positions relative to each other.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="region-fixed-time-motion">
			<title>Fixed-time motion</title>
			<para>
				Sometimes, you want to move a region to another track, but keeping its
				position along the timeline exactly the same. To do this, use
				<mousebutton>Button2</mousebutton> rather than <mousebutton>Button1</mousebutton>.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="copying-regions">
		<title>Copying Regions</title>
		<para>
			To copy a region, make sure you are in <emphasis>object</emphasis> mouse
			mode. Move the mouse pointer into the waveform press the
			<keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key, keep it down while pressing
			<mousebutton>Button1</mousebutton> and drag. A new region is created and will
			follow the mouse pointer as it moves. See <xref linkend="moving-regions"/> for
			more details on moving the copied region around.
		</para>

		<section id="copying-more-than-one-region">
			<title>Copying more than one region</title>
			<para>
				To copy multiple regions, select them before copying. Then click+drag on
				one of the selected regions. All the regions will be copied and as they
				move, the will keep their positions relative to each other.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="region-fixed-time-copying">
			<title>Fixed-time copying</title>
			<para>
				If you want to copy region(s) to other track(s) but keep the copies at the
				exact position on the timeline as the originals, simply use
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><mousebutton>Button2</mousebutton></keycombo> instead of
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><mousebutton>Button1</mousebutton></keycombo>.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="trimming-regions">
		<title>Trimming Regions</title>
		<para></para>
	</section>

	<section id="auditioning-regions">
		<title>Auditioning Regions</title>
		<para></para>
	</section>

	<section id="region-gain-envelopes">
		<title>Region Gain Envelopes</title>
		<para></para>
	</section>

	<section id="region-context-menu">
		<!-- needs work -->
		<title>Region Context Menu</title>
		<para>
			If you context-click on a region, a popup menu will appear. At or near the
			top of that menu is a list of all regions that exist in the clicked-upon
			track under the mouse pointer. Each region entry (shown by name) points to
			a submenu that contains region-specific operations:
		</para>

		<variablelist>
			<title></title>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Popup region editor</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						creates and displays the editor for this region, allowing even more
						specific control over the region than this menu
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Raise to top layer</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						moves the region to the top layer of this track (works only in "Most
						recently added/moved/trimmed regions are higher" <emphasis>layer
						mode</emphasis>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Lower to bottom layer</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						moves the region to the bottom layer of this track (works only in "Most
						recently added/moved/trimmed regions are higher" <emphasis>layer
						mode</emphasis>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Define sync point</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						if the edit cursor is within this region, defines the region sync point
						at the edit cursor location.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Remove sync point</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para></para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Audition</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						plays this region via the <glossterm linkend="gt-auditioner">auditioner</glossterm>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Export</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						exports this region to a new audio file, via the export dialog (thus
						allowing resampling, dithering, format specification etc.)
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Bounce</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						re-records this region (with any plugins/inserts applied) to a new audio
						file, and replaces the region with one referring to the new file.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Lock</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						prevents the region from being moved, trimmed, or modified in almost any
						way.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Unlock</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						removes the lock on region modification
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Mute</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						makes the region silent during playback
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Unmute</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para></para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Toggle envelope visibility</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						shows/hides the region gain envelope
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Toggle envelope active</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						turns the region gain envelope on/off (the line is gray when the
						envelope is off, green when it is on)
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Original position</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						if the region was recorded (and Broadcast WAVE was the native file
						format) moves the region to its original capture position
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Normalize</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						alters the gain processing of the region so that the loudest sample is
						at 0dBFS
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>DeNormalize</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						undoes the effect of a normalize
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Reverse</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						writes the region to a new audio file with the contents reversed, and
						replaces the region with one referring to the new file
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Nudge</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						moves the region in various ways
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Nudge fwd</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						moves the region forward by the amount shown in the nudge clock
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Nudge bwd</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						moves the region backward by the amount shown in the nudge clock
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Nudge fwd by capture offset</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						moves the region forward by the same offset that it might have been
						(incorrectly) adjusted by when captured
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Nudge bwd by capture offset</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						moves the region backwards by the same offset that it might have been
						(incorrectly) adjusted by when captured
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Trim</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para></para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Start to edit cursor</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						adjusts the start of the region to the current position of the edit
						cursor (if possible)
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Edit cursor to end</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						adjusts the end of the region to the current position of the edit cursor
						(if possible)
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Split</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						if the edit cursor is within the region, splits the region at the editor
						cursor location
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Make mono regions</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						if the region is a multi-channel one, creates new regions corresponding
						to each channel. The new regions are added to the editor's region list,
						not the track.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Duplicate</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						pops up a dialog allowing the region to be copied 1 or more times. Each
						copy is placed directly after the original or previous copy.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Fill Track</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						copies the region as many times as necessary to fill the track to the
						current session end mark. Each copy is placed directly after the
						original or previous copy.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Remove</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						remove the region from the track (non-destructive)
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><guilabel>Destroy</guilabel></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						remove the region from the track and the editor region list, and if no
						other regions are referencing it, remove the audio file that the region
						is derived from. ( <emphasis>DESTRUCTIVE</emphasis> )
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section>
<!--
	<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
		href="Some_Subsection.xml" />
	-->
</section>
